Houston Ship Channel 50th Anniversary Collection, 1926-1964
University of Houston Libraries
Houston Ship Channel 50th Anniversary Collection
1926-1964
1982-001
University of Houston Libraries
Although the Buffalo Bayou had been used for boat navigation in Houston as early as 1839, the Houston Ship Channel was established in 1914. In 1841, the mayor of Houston established the Port of Houston, which was supported by the city and later by the state of Texas. In 1880, Congressional legislation was introduced which began the involvement of the federal government in the Ship Channel. There are 66 items in the collection, dating from 1926-1964. Included is a typed manuscript history of the Port of Houston and Buffalo Bayou, a typed version of the ordinance establishing the Port of Houston, and photos documenting the history of the Port of Houston.
1 box; 66 items
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
Historical Note
The Houston Ship Channel was established in 1914; however, Buffalo Bayou, which flows through Houston, had been used for boat navigation as early as 1839. In 1841, the mayor of Houston established the Port of Houston, which was supported by the city and later by the state of Texas. In 1880, Congressional legislation was introduced which began the involvement of the federal government in the Ship Channel.
The Houston Ship Channel was completed in 1914, although many additional improvements and changes have been made since that date. These include the dredging of the turning basin, allowing for larger ships to navigate the channel, and widening the entrance to the channel.
Several books have been written about the Port of Houston. For additional information, see:
Sibley, Marilyn McAdams. The Port of Houston: A History. Austin: University of Texas Press, 1968.
Ball, Thomas Henry. The Port of Houston: How It Came to Pass. Houston, Tex., 1944.
Scope and Contents
There are 66 items in the collection, dating from 1926-1964. Included is a typed manuscript history of the Port of Houston and Buffalo Bayou, as well as a typed version of the ordinance establishing the Port of Houston, in 1841.
In addition are 40 photographic prints. The photographs include shots of an exhibit highlighting the history of the Port of Houston, as well as photographs from the fiftieth anniversary of the Port of Houston, taken on November 10, 1964. The anniversary photographs were taken at the Shamrock Hilton and on Wharf Number 25 at the Ship Channel. People in these photographs have not been identified.
Two items were removed from the collection for cataloging. One of the items is a pamphlet, “Buffalo Bayou and the Houston Ship Channel, 1820-1926.” The other item is a promotional broadside, showing the layout of the city of Houston and railroads in the area.
Index Terms
Terms are either Library of Congress Subject Headings or taken from local sources.
Subjects
Harbors Texas History.; Harbors Texas Houston
Formats
Photographs; Typescripts
Acquisition
The collection of materials was donated to Special Collections by Edward L. Horn in 1982.
Access Restrictions
Open for research.
Detailed Description
  - An ordinance establishing the Port., [1841] (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Story of Buffalo Bayou., 1926 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photographs--Exhibit., [1964] (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Photographs--Exhibit., [1964] (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Photographs--Exhibit., [1964] (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Photographs--Exhibit., [1964] (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Photographs--Fiftieth Anniversary., 1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Photographs--Fiftieth Anniversary., 1964 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Photographs--Fiftieth Anniversary., 1964 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Photographs--Fiftieth Anniversary., 1964 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Photographs--Fiftieth Anniversary., 1964 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Photographs--Fiftieth Anniversary., 1964 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Photographs--Fiftieth Anniversary., 1964 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Photographs--Fiftieth Anniversary., 1964 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Photographs--Fiftieth Anniversary., 1964 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Photographs--Fiftieth Anniversary., 1964 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Photographs--Fiftieth Anniversary., 1964 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Photographs--Fiftieth Anniversary., 1964 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Photographs--Fiftieth Anniversary., 1964 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Photographs--Fiftieth Anniversary., 1964 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Photographs--Fiftieth Anniversary., 1964 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Photographs--Fiftieth Anniversary., 1964 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Photographs--Fiftieth Anniversary., 1964 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Photographs--Fiftieth Anniversary., 1964 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Photographs--Fiftieth Anniversary., 1964 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Photographs--Fiftieth Anniversary., 1964 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Photographs--Fiftieth Anniversary., 1964 (Box 1, Folder 27)